but he said literally quote my body is
failing when he announced this thing
that he was going to go to the hospital
to get checked up to see what was up
that was scary until we got an update
I'm going to get out there I'm going to
say it I'm going to say it I have I've
not said that competitive CrossFit is
dying but I've said that competitive
CrossFit is getting a little less
popular or is less popular than it has
been in recent years some viewership
numbers that suggests competitive
CrossFit not going anywhere might be
getting even more popular
once the co lockdowns were lifted and
everybody could go back to the gyms they
just had all of this equipment and no
demand for
it welcome to strength weekly the show
that brings you everything you need to
know from around the barbell game and
maybe the bow Flex game as well for bar
band.com the official media partner of
you we're your favorite right I'm David
Thomas to joined by Phil Blackman Phil
we got a lot to talk about today
including some stuff on the business of
Fitness but we also have world record
squats cuz we know people like the big
weights blex files for
bankruptcy and is getting acquired for
about $37 million we'll talk about the
future potentially of that iconic
Fitness brand reminds me of some late
night infomercials from the 9s we also
have a world record ipf squat CrossFit
the CrossFit open breaking some live
streaming numbers which I got to be
honest it's a little surprising to me
and then Samson dauda last year's Arnold
classic bodybuilding champion this
year's runnerup has a medical scare
which opens up conversation around
frequency of competition for elite
bodybuilders we will get into that and
when we will see him take the stage next
Phil of these stories which are you most
excited about this week I'm I'm most
excited to actually talk about duda's
story uh because that was a a fast
turnaround on our story of big breaking
news followed by an update followed by
like what we can look forward to next so
I think that that that's going to be our
punchiest story for today yeah punchiest
is a great way of putting it all right
we'll dive in on March 5th 2024 the Year
we're in right now Boflex the iconic
Fitness brand filed for chapter 11
bankruptcy now Boflex has been around
for quite some time they have been a
publicly traded company really a penny
stock for quite a bit of time they
offloaded the Nautilus brand for around
$10 million last year November 2023 in
order to get some cash wasn't enough and
now they bankrupt now chapter 11
bankruptcy means we will continue to see
Boflex but they are being
acquired by a different Fitness company
and will no longer remain independent
Phil what details can you give us there
yeah so the the real Fallout of this
whole story for blex was coming out of
the pandemic so as covid hit and there
were lockdowns and people wanted to be
able to train at home there was a huge
surge in home fitness equipment that
Boflex wanted to capitalize on so they
increased the amount of productivity
that they were going to use to try and
capitalize on those that demand for the
Home Gyms and everything that they could
supply for people in lockdowns because
we didn't know when the quarantine would
be lifted and when everything would open
back up including most gyms so they
capitalized on that but then once the
covid lockdowns were lifted and
everybody could go back to the gyms they
just had all of this equipment and no
demand for it and that just left them
with a bunch of Supply that they
couldn't offload and now they ran into
these problems where now they're trying
to sell some Brands and they're trying
to sell that equipment and figure out
what they can do and just not enough not
in enough time so it was a real roller
coaster of like we're in lockdowns we're
doing great we're out of lockdowns we're
doing bad and worth noting that Boflex
will be acquired by Johnson Health Tech
and blex will continue to operate so
basically they have worked out kind of a
debt financing deal and a debt deal to
where they will be able to continue to
operate pay their bills pay their
employees they just won't be independent
anymore and it's a massive massive shift
for a brand that really thought they
could double down on the home fitness
Trend during the pandemic I want to
point out this is something indicative
of what we've seen from a lot of massive
Fitness companies coming out of the
pandemic the prime example of this once
a Wall Street darling was pelaton
pelaton a publicly traded company did
massively well during the pandemic their
stock was at an all-time high I got a
pelaton during the pandemic just like a
lot of people coming out of the pandemic
they have had a difficult time keeping
up with that surge demand has dropped
for atome fitness equipment people are
not necessarily working out at home
they're out and about or in gyms doesn't
mean we're going to see Boflex going
anywhere um but offloading the Nautilus
brand which they did last year
rebranding to blex wasn't enough to save
them did not create enough Capital to
save them so we will see them in a
different form moving forward but if you
are a Boflex user if you're looking to
buy Boflex equipment it's still
available online it's not like it's
going anywhere it's just the company's
going to be in a different form we're
still seeing the Ripple effects of
pandemic Fitness of what the pandemic
did to the fitness industry 100% yeah I
mean the what happened during that time
where the companies were making
decisions during lockdowns and during
covid was an unpredictable circumstance
like how how is anybody supposed to know
the correct decisions to make in that
kind of environment but what also
happened that helped that I mean
effectively diluted these decisions as
well is a bunch of new companies also
trying to capitalize on the demand for
Home Fitness during that time so not
only were they trying to meet demand but
now the competition in that space Also
expanded so not only do you have higher
competition more competition but now you
also have to meet this demand that you
don't know how long it's going for how
long it's safe like when the and then we
saw it all fell out when the quarantines
were lifted and your experience is very
similar to mine in that people are
training outside of back in their gyms
and their Fitness Studios and what have
you if anything I would think that the
the roller coaster has just shifted for
that type of Outlet your your functional
fitness Studios is really where I feel
like people have moved back to now that
they can go and train again and we're
going to talk a little bit about because
CrossFit actually is releasing some data
that suggests they're doing pretty well
we'll that in in in a few minutes but
first we got a powerlifting world record
a junior world record but want to note
powerlifting Junior World Records go up
to 23 years and weightlifting they only
go up to 20 years powerlifting juniors
go up to 23 Phil I intro a lot of
stories I'm gonna ask would you be so
kind as to intro this one because you
know what I think it's what the people
want I sure can Antonio Perez baros in
the 105 kg weight class he said an ipf
Junior raw squat world record of 335 kg
at the 2024 EPF European powerlifting
Federation European University Cup in
Nancy France on March 3rd 2024 he
secured the gold medal and he scored uh
his world record lift in the squat and
that's just around 740 pounds for those
who don't speak kilos I know if you're
watching this you're a strength weekly
uh viewer you're a Barb and reader you
speak kilos probably but around 740
pounds now Antonio uh was able to set
this this was an international meet
right a European champion ship level
meet so you're able eligible to set
world records has to be that
International meet only actually missed
one lift on uh the day he had a 350 kilo
deadlift attempt which he missed so he
goes eight for nine pretty pretty darn
good performance interesting thing about
Antonio something missing from his
resume as a young lifter this is last
year as a junior lifter in powerlifting
does not have that Junior World
Championship however uh his top level
competition for the last few years has
aged out of the junior division so it
might be his time to claim that Junior
World title which is kind of the thing
missing Phil Let's Pretend We're Dr
Squat for a second how would you
diagnose this lift my friend one thing
about bars' lifting particularly in the
squat is it's very clean it has to be
his top lift his three attempts up to
his world record squat was a 300
kilogram left a 320 kilogram left and
then of course his world record or his
uh junior world record at 335 so he's
got a heavy Squat and that's really
where he's going to be able to set the
pace going into his attempt for a world
championship his squat is clean there's
there's not really a fundamental flaw in
his technique he's a he's very heavy in
the squad and I just think that like if
he's going to win big at the world
championships and actually claim that as
his last piece of Hardware before going
into the open he's got to put on a big
performance in the squat which he
clearly can do and I expect him at the
World Championships to at least call for
to match his Junior world record and
break it so I expect his Junior world
record weight to be called on his second
lift before he tries to break it on his
third his squat clearly get strong but
we do see a trajectory it's not all
powerlifters this is a bit an anecdotal
but we see a lot of Junior powerlifters
you know their squat will get to that
Elite status even at the open level
among all lifters much quicker than the
bench and deadlift the bench is
something that we see folks add on
significant amount of Weights uh weight
during their 20s some of it's technique
right some of it's muscle maturity some
of it's just Mass you know one of the
most interesting things I remember
talking to Kevin Oak himself a very
accomplished world record setting power
lifter a few years ago and he was like
listen the lift that is most dependent
on just muscle maturity and muscle mass
is the bench press which is why there's
the smallest discrepancy often between
bodybuilders when it comes to uh between
bodybuilders and pters when it comes to
the bench press he's like that is the
lift where you you know bodybuilders and
power lifters can kind of like get
together and there's not a cosmic
difference in what they're moving so
interesting and I think that for Antonio
lifters like him we will see additions
to their totals come from the bench
press as they reach the mid 20s it just
takes time it takes time to add kilos to
that lift and to add that upper body
strength a little bit slower than it
might on the squat and then deadlift
also takes some time to come but
interesting to see him go for 350 on the
deadlift and uh you know hopefully
something by the time the world champion
Junior World Championships rolls around
uh he might be able to hit and add some
significant um some significant poundage
some significant kilos to his total Phil
I'm going to take back the Reigns and
intro the third story here today
I'm gonna get out there I'm gonna say it
I'm gonna say it I have I've not said
that competitive CrossFit is dying but
I've said that competitive CrossFit one
man's opinion I've said competitive
CrossFit is getting a little less
popular or is less popular than it has
been in recent years that's probably my
own personal bias there's some new
viewership numbers from the most recent
CrossFit open announcement
24.2 which was that 20 minute am wrap of
300 meter rows 10 deadlifts and 50
double ERS I mean brutal I did not do
that one yet I might try and tackle it
this week some data some viewership
numbers that suggest competitive
CrossFit not going anywhere might be
even getting even more popular the live
stream announcement hosted by WWE
Superstar Seth Rollins and taking place
live from uh Justin madero's home gem
The Shred Shed set alltime concurrent
viewership numbers for a CrossFit open
announcement Phil do we have those
numbers handy because uh a lot of lot of
lot of digits yes let's get into the
details the 24.2 announcement had a Max
viewership now this is unofficial but we
had a Max viewership of over 200,000
with a total view count after 24 hours
eclipsing 800,000 which is very very
strong you compare that to the under
200,000 for 24.1 that is an
exceptionally large percentage shift
getting Seth Rollins who is a cross a
CrossFit athlete himself he's been Cally
known as the CrossFit Jesus for a very
long time bringing his kind of star
power to the live announcement I mean
that's the big variable shift here I
mean granted we were also the live
announcement took place in a two-time
fittest man on Earth's personal gym
which I'm sure had some play to it as
well but like the real big variable here
is adding star power outside of the
CrossFit world even though it's related
because he is a CrossFit athlete that
really changed the numbers and I can see
them wanting to really delve into that
like where are the other CrossFit
athletes outside of actual competitive
cross CrossFit that they can lean into
to bring in a different audience it's
interesting for me to see yeah to see
that crossover it's not just Dave Castro
you know in a random CrossFit gym uh you
know live streamed on on Facebook and
YouTube and and the CrossFit game site
they are bringing on like bringing on
guests hosts really trying to
cross-pollinate the social reach that
CrossFit stars have with other athletes
or other celebrities who do who are
crossfitters as well I think it's a
really smart move I would say personally
I feel like the CrossFit games has
gotten a little
less popular but that might just be me
getting a little less invested or being
a little less invested in it post
pandemic since the days of Matt when
Matt Fraser was competing right I just
feel like the stakes are a little lower
and I feel like people aren't so
invested in a lot of folks I know are
just kind of not as engaged with the
competitive season yeah I think it's
actually an amalgam of a couple of
different factors that have gotten to
that what I think is a reasonable
conclusion to be honest but the the big
one from this season that I think really
you know put that on the radar was the
fact that they lost their title sponsor
so there's no title sponsor the only
real response that can be to that is
wait could they not find a title sponsor
because it would be weird to not want a
title sponsor you think that you'd want
as many sponsors as possible I do want
to be careful there I do want to say
like we don't we don't know we don't
know no of course we don't know that
that that's and I think also like there
is something to be said I me I remember
when Reebok became the title sponsor
well over a decade ago at this point it
was a big deal cuz Reebok was a bigger
more household name than CrossFit was
right obviously a title sponsor it' be
quick to assume that not having a title
sponsor is a bad thing for CrossFit
because they've had it for so long but
also like you know the Super Bowl
doesn't have a title sponsor the NBA
championships don't have a tit it's not
you know it's not the Nike NBA
championships it's not the Adidas Super
Bowl right so like I just I do want to
be careful because that was my first
reaction but at the same time you know
the sport it might be a good sign it
might be a signal the sport wants to
stand on its own two feet a little bit
not having that title sponsor like with
the name of the championship so I don't
know it's tough to say you just got me
that excellent segue the initial
reaction is okay there's no title
sponsor that obviously is indicative of
something bad right however this is also
the first season where they've broken
off the adapted divisions the age group
and teen divisions to stand alone on
their own so this is the first time
where the games are going to be separate
which could lead to oh this is actually
a different trajectory that CrossFit is
taking to build the games up to be
bigger than that and so the the one two
punch of wait is this bad oh wait a
minute then is this good that's where I
think like if that transition period if
that's what they're actually going for
that might lead to a slight dip in
viewership as people are like figuring
out what this new ground actually looks
like so I I think that there's some
amount of that that's influencing it
also as you mentioned there isn't like
the top of the the the dominant athlete
in the sport anymore we're not in a a
Froning or fras Frasier ERA last year we
didn't have Tumi so like we're watching
watching the games going wait a minute
these are obviously the the best in the
world but we know that the the best in
the world that's been the best in the
world isn't here so is this sort of an
interim Championship like what does this
actually mean like we need to get the
best of the best year because they
haven't actually retired yet Tia Tumi
hasn't retired yet she just took a break
for a season to start a family and now
she's going to be back this season so I
expect all of that to actually culminate
to the numbers returning to some
favorability this year there's a lot of
buildup to the 2024 games and a lot of
variables both on thei and off and I
think that's going to show I would
predict that we will see an increase
back to what are the favorable expected
numbers for the games that bring it back
to the levels that we've seen previously
and hopefully that also Sparks your
interest back up into it because as
somebody who's been on the beat of all
of these different things for the last
several months I think that like it's
tough to see through all of them
together you know what I mean Phil well
said I had like four more points and you
eclipsed them all so I I think that I
was I just want to say I was scratching
my earlier this year with some of the
decisions it seemed like CrossFit was
making and to me my first pessimistic
reaction was oo does this does this
spell bad things for competitive
CrossFit I I think I might have been
wrong and these viewership numbers with
help from Seth Rollins suggest that
maybe I was a little premature so you
know what I'll eat some Crow on that one
and honestly like we want to see all
strength Sports Thrive I think it's a
really important Point even when on this
broadcast we get into opinion and we're
critical like we want to see string
Sports Drive I started barbend right I
started barbend because I love string
Sports and I wanted to see them grow and
I thought they would grow I thought it
was a good business decision to start a
media company in the space so I just
want to point out even when I sound
really pessimistic it's just me being
kind of a crotchy old guy it's not
because I don't love this stuff I want
to see CrossFit grow like I I I want to
see all of these Sports grow and Thrive
because I think they make people's lives
better and I love them too so you know
much love to CrossFit really cool to see
these numbers like super super positive
note from me let's talk about something
else that was a was a a bit of a roller
coaster of a story men's open
bodybuilding competitor 2023 Arnold
Classic champ and 2023 Olympia Podium
finisher Samson dauda who finished
behind hotti shupin at the 2024 Arnold
Classic in a hotley contested contest
had a bit of healthc care right after
the Arnold Classic just just a week or
so ago as of this recording it was a
story that where a lot was evolving very
quickly Roger lockeridge covered it for
barbend we got some quotes from Samson
uh Phil what what was going on kind of
take us through the chronology of what
happened with Samson here so uh Samson
competed at the 2024 all classic as you
mentioned he got second place losing his
championship to hotti shupin who was the
2022 Mr Olympia hotti after losing the
Olympia to drik Lunsford in uh 2023 he
had to come back and put on a
performance to prove that he still got
it that he's still the number one
Contender he did so in really really
incredible fashion at in Columbus here
in
2024 we got to hear from Tyler Manion
who was one of the head judges at uh the
Arnold Classic uh comparing those two
guys Samson and hotti were the top two
guys it was very clear they were in
their own call out multiple times just
the two of them going up against each
other and uh Tyler effectively said that
it wasn't all that close hottie's
conditioning was just so far in away
beyond anything else that like it's the
best package they've ever seen from
hotti including at from the Olympia that
he's going to be really tough to to to
beat if athletes can't match that kind
of conditioning there's an extra level
of conditioning hotti is just so good on
that on that side of things that like d
has to come up but D is already down to
such a low body fat percentage when he
competes obviously all these guys are
but he also has obligations to his
sponsors at like big events with like at
the Arnold sports festival you have the
Expo and so daa on very low body fat
percentage on low calories he still went
to the Expo he still was at the Celsius
Booth where he you know meet and greeted
guests and all that stuff and he thinks
that post competition he got some kind
of sickness and he wasn't sure exactly
what it was but he said literally quote
my body is failing when he announced
this thing that he was going to go to
the hospital to get checked up to see
what was up that was scary until we got
an update so that that that was like my
body is failing everybody's Minds went
to all of the other athletes that's H
that that's happened to in the past
where we've seen like you know
unfortunate and premature deaths like we
were like everybody was like super
concerned like what is going on like d
we get get to the hospital like take a
break like don't run in don't don't make
a mistake that we've seen before where
athletes push themselves too hard so
everybody was on high alert including
everybody at barbin we get an update
after he goes to the hospital we find
out that he it was some kind of flu he
just needed some kind of antibiotics to
get off of it like obviously it was from
being depleted it was from getting sick
at the at the Arnold he received
antibiotics he was cleared by his doctor
to compete he still expected to compete
at the Arnold Classic UK which is
happening this weekend the the 14th to
the 17th it's a really short time from
when he announced that he his body was
failing and that he was sick to him
returning to competition potentially
he's cleared to compete he's expected to
compete at what level he will be able to
compete at that's something that we're
going to watch for but it was a real
roller coaster of people really really
concerned to okay it's just a flu he's
got antibiotics everything seems to be
okay but it does beg the question should
there be a minimum time frame between
which athletes can compete at Pro shows
first off great to hear Samson's feeling
better we obviously wish him the best
bodybuilding especially in his division
an incredibly taxing thing I don't think
anyone's going to get on this broadcast
and claim that's a healthy lifestyle
right and and we are certainly not
presenting it as such I want to point
out right we want to know for folks
watching do you think there should be a
minimum amount of time required for
elite bodybuilders competing between
shows basically should they have to take
a certain amount of time off be between
professional stage appearances now
that's something that you know the ifbb
or other bodybuilding federations could
Institute they could say if you're a pro
you need to take four months between
competitions or you need to take six
months between competitions right that's
something they could do currently it's
not something that's on the books but I
think that you know these back-to-back
competition schedules sort of beg the
question because it does leave athletes
vulnerable whether they're immuno
compromised whether they're vulnerable
in other ways because these athletes
they're not when they're on stage no
one's going to claim they're the
healthiest no one's going to claim
they're thriving they might look ripped
they might look Yol they might look
amazing but are they thriving from a
holistic health perspective no
absolutely not so I'm just curious what
people think and this is something that
you know when Phil and I were planning
out this episode we were like hey should
we talk about this I wonder what folks
think should there be a minimum time
between shows for pro bodybuilders um
just curious to have the discussion when
you only have to show up once and
compete and hit it's like that's a it's
a much easier thing to do than if you're
competing three times four times six
times over the course of a season
it's really tough to Peak on peak week
and to do it like every two months every
three months like that's really steep
that's really difficult on your system
and against incentives they're economic
incentives right sponsor incentives
prize person incentives to compete right
at the same time they are Health
incentives to not compete sometimes and
to not put that stress on your body in
those short time frames so that brings
us to the end of this week's strength
weekly broadcast for Barb and.com I'm
David Thomas toow joined by the
incomparable and hopefully well rested
Phil Blackman we'll catch you all next
week appreciate
it